<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truth cleared of scandals, or truth lifting up its head above scandals, &amp;c. Occasioned by the meeting of those people called Baptists, and those whom the world scornfully calleth Quakers, at Harlington in stafforthshire, upon the 27. day of the 7 month, in the year 1654. Shewing the difference betwixt the ordinances of Christ and of Antichrist, and the true worship and the false, with a discovery of the two seeds, and the New Covenant, the doctrine of baptismes, laying on of hands, the ressurectio, and eternal judgement, Heb. 6. 1, 2, 3, and Heb. 12.22, and 23. Also, the unprofitable servant and the talents, and of being caught up into paradise, the thorn in the flesh, and what it is to take pleasure in infirmities, and what those infirmities are, that is to be gloried in; also, something of perfection, and imperfection, and the glorying in the crosse largely proved, according to scripture, &amp;c. / By one known to the world by the name of Rich. Fanrworth.</title>
            <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F512</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E820_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207345</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866402</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866402</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118674</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85152)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118674)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 125:E820[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truth cleared of scandals, or truth lifting up its head above scandals, &amp;c. Occasioned by the meeting of those people called Baptists, and those whom the world scornfully calleth Quakers, at Harlington in stafforthshire, upon the 27. day of the 7 month, in the year 1654. Shewing the difference betwixt the ordinances of Christ and of Antichrist, and the true worship and the false, with a discovery of the two seeds, and the New Covenant, the doctrine of baptismes, laying on of hands, the ressurectio, and eternal judgement, Heb. 6. 1, 2, 3, and Heb. 12.22, and 23. Also, the unprofitable servant and the talents, and of being caught up into paradise, the thorn in the flesh, and what it is to take pleasure in infirmities, and what those infirmities are, that is to be gloried in; also, something of perfection, and imperfection, and the glorying in the crosse largely proved, according to scripture, &amp;c. / By one known to the world by the name of Rich. Fanrworth.</title>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35, [1]p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed, Anno Dom. 1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 15".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118674:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>TRUTH Cleared of Scandals, or TRUTH lifting up its head above Scandals,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Occaſioned by the Meeting of thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple called Baptiſts, and thoſe whom the world ſcornfully calleth Quakers. at</hi> Harliſton in Stafforth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, upon the <hi>27.</hi> day of the <hi>7.</hi> month, in the year <hi>1654.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shewing the difference betwixt the Ordinances of</hi> Christ and of Antichrist, and the true worſhip and the falſe, with a Diſcovery of the two ſeeds, and the New Covenant, the Doctrine of Baptiſmes, laying on of hands, the Reſurrection, and eternall judgement, Heb. <hi>6.1, 2, 3,</hi> and Heb. <hi>12.22,</hi> and <hi>23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo, The unprofitable ſervant and the talents, and of being caught up into Paradiſe, the Thorn</hi> in the fleſh, and what it is to take pleaſure in infirmities, and what thoſe infirmities are, that is to be gloried in; Alſo, ſomething of Perfection, and Imperfection, and the glorying in the Croſſe largely prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, according to Scripture, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By one known to the world by the name of RICH. FARNWORTH.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>For Chriſt ſent me not to Baptize, but to preach the Goſpel, not with the enticing words of mans wiſdome, neither, leſt the Croſſe of Chriſt ſhould be of none effect,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 1.17. and 18.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON, Printed,</hi> Anno Dom. <hi>1654.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118674:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118674:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Reading of this enſuing Treatiſe, as thy underſtanding is kept open, thou may ſee the difference betwixt Truth and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, that thereby thou mayeſt chuſe the good and refuſe the evill; <hi>try all things and hold faſt that which is good,</hi> and take heed of cenſuring or judging the truth with evill thoughts, and out of an evill heart, leſt judgement return upon thee again, but judge Righteous judgement, ſo ſhalt thou be preſerved in Peace in thy Conſcience. The cauſe of my writing of this little Treatiſe, was occaſioned upon a Meeting at <hi>Harliſton</hi> in <hi>Stafforth</hi> Shire, upon the <hi>27.</hi> day of the <hi>7.</hi> month, between the baptized people, and thoſe whom the world ſcornfully calleth Quakers, to clear the Truth of many aſperſions, and falſe accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as in the Reading thou wilt clearly ſee the differences betwixt Truth and errour, as thou Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt with an underſtanding: And whereas we are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed for denying the Scriptures and the Ordinances of Chriſt, in ſhort, thou mayeſt ſee what we own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Scripture, and what we do deny, that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Scripture; alſo the tryall of the Spirits,
<pb facs="tcp:118674:3"/>and the Doctrine of Baptiſmes, and the laying on of hands, and the Reſurrection and eternall Judgement, true Faith, the Church of the firſt-born written in heaven: Something of them ſpoken of in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, which may be for the bringing down of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Antichriſt, and the ſetting up of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Jeſus Chriſt, that Truth may be cleared of Scandals: But I am not ſent to Baptize, but to Preach the Goſpel, as in thy Reading thou wilt more plainly ſee.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>RICH. FARNWORTH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118674:3"/>
            <head>THE ORDINANCES AND VVORSHIP <hi>Of GOD in the Spirit.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>GOD is a Spirit, and all his Ordinances are Spirituall, now in the Goſpel-Miniſtration, and his Worſhip is in the Spirit, as it is written, <hi>John</hi> 4.23, 24. And the Worſhip and Ordinances of God in the Spirit we own, who are of the Circumciſion in the heart, with the Spirit, who rejoice in Chriſt Jeſus, and have no confidence in the fleſh, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.10, 11. Now the Lord is that Spirit which we all beholding with open face, as in a Glaſſe, are changed from glory to glory into the ſame image and glory, as by the Spirit of the Lord, as it is written, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17, 18.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, the Church of God and of Chriſt we own, who are the houſhold of Faith, made all of living ſtones, elect and precious, a Spirituall houſe for God to dwell in, whoſe houſe are we, who are build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles, Chriſt Jeſus being the Chief Corner Stone in whom all the building groweth into an holy Temple in the Lord, the Church of the firſt-born, written in heaven, of which Chriſt Jeſus is head, and we are compleat in him who is the fulneſſe, and filleth all in all, as it is written and witneſſed. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 2.5, 6, <hi>&amp;c. Heb.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.22, 23. <hi>and Heb.</hi> 12.22, 23. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.18, 19, 20, 21, 22. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.9.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, the Miniſtery of Chriſt in the Spirit we own, and the new Covenant, and the Law of God written in the heart, and we witneſſe the teachings of the Lord as he hath promiſed and ſaid, which promiſes of the Father we witneſſe fulfilling and fulfilled, and we witneſſe Chriſt Jeſus
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118674:4"/>who is the Saints high Prieſt, and the everlaſting Sacrifice; we witneſſe and own the Fathers teachings according to his Promiſe, and we witneſs Chriſt Jeſus to be our Paſſover, and that he is able to ſave to the utermoſt all thoſe that come unto God by him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10, 11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.31. <hi>to the</hi> 35. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.13, 14. <hi>John</hi> 6.45. <hi>John</hi> 14.15, 16, 17. <hi>and</hi> 26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Baptiſm of Chriſt which is in the Spirit we own, and all who are Baptized into the Name of the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt, and are made partakers of the Name, nature, and properties of God; for he that hath the Son, hath life, and he that hath the Son hath the Father alſo, as Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>All mine are thine, and thine are mine, and I am glorified in them;</hi> and by one Spirit are we baptized into one body, and made to drink in one Spirit, where there is one Faith, one Lord, one Baptiſme, one God and Father of us all, who are of the righteous ſeed, who are Baptized into Chriſt, and have put on Chriſt, as it is written and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18, 19, 20, 21. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>John</hi> 17.10. 2 <hi>John</hi> 9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12, 13. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.4, 5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26, 27, 28, 29.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Prayer we own, Praying by the Spirit of Chriſt, and if any man be in Chriſt Jeſus he is a new creature, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16, 17. and walks not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit, and the ſame Spirit which raiſed up Jeſus Chriſt from the dead, we witneſſe dwelling in us, by which Spirit we are quickened, even by the Spirit of Chriſt that dwelleth in us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.10, 11. And we know that all that are born again of water, and the Spirit, and are led by the Spirit of God, they are the Sons of God, and we have received the Spirit of Adoption, whereby we cry Abba Father, the Spirit it ſelf bearing witnes with our ſpirits that we are the children of God, <hi>Rom</hi> 8.14, 15, 16. Likewiſe the Spirit helpeth us, and teacheth us to pray, for it maketh interceſſion for us, and he that ſearcheth the hearts, knoweth what is the minde of the Spirit, becauſe he maketh interceſſion for us according to the minde and will of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26, 27. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.18.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, the holy Communion in the Spirit of love, that we witneſſe; for God is love, and they that dwell in God dwell in love, and they that dwell in love dwell in God, and God in them, and herein is our love made perfect, as it is written, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.16, 17, 18. And we own all thoſe who abide in the doctrine of Chriſt, ſuch as have fellowſhip with the Father, and the Son, and the reſt we deny, as we are required, and as it is written and witneſſed <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11. 2 <hi>Iohn</hi> 9, 10, 11. But that communion in the Spirit we own, which the Saints have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in with the Father and the Son, and the Cup of bleſſing and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the blood of Chriſt we own, which the Saints drink in by the Spirit into one Body, as it is written and witneſſed. 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0.15, 16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. And as Chriſt hath ſaid, He that eats my fleſh, and drinks my bloud dwelleth in me, and I in him; and the bread of life and the living food we witneſſe, ſpoken of in <hi>Iohn</hi> the 6, And the fruit of the Vine, and the Cup of bleſſing, which is the Communion of the Blood or life of Chriſt, who is the Vine and the vertue, and the bread of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118674:4"/>life for ſouls to ſeed on, and live, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.52, 53, 54. <hi>to the</hi> 59. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15 And you that are ſpirituall, judge ye what I ſay, The bread which we break, is it not the Communion of the Body of Chriſt, and the Cup which we drink, is it not the Communion of the Bloud of Chriſt; for we being many, are one Bread, and one Body, as it is written and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and we are partakers of that one Bread, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.15, 16, 17. Which Bread is Chriſt the Bread of life which our ſouls ſeeds on dayly, and liveth; for ever praiſed be the Lord. <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.48, 52, 58.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Singing with the Spirit and the underſtanding that we own, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. and we know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an underſtanding to know him that is true, and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt; and this is true God, and life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, as it is written and witneſſed, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.20. but to ſing <hi>Davids</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions in Rime and Meeter, as the world that lyeth in wicked and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the underſtanding do, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.19. that we deny, and againſt it teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie; but Hymnes and ſpirituall Songs with grace in the heart, that we own, as it is written and witneſſed, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.15, 16. and to ſing with the Spirit and the underſtanding new Songs, which none can learn but thoſe that are redeemed from the earth, that we own who are redeemed and witneſſe, as it is written, <hi>Rev</hi> 5.9, 10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>Eightly, Preaching by the Spirit we own, by which Faith comes in the hearing of the Son, which is ſent of the Father, preaching to the Spirits in priſon, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19. and all that are ſent by the Spirit, and are of the Seed Royall, ſuch we own, as it is written and witneſſed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.21. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.16, 17.</p>
            <p>And all who are annointed by the Spirit to Preach, which Preacheth by the Spirit, and giveth freely as they have received freely, ſuch we own, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. <hi>Ch.</hi> and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61. and all ſuch we own as are ſanctified, and ſent of the Father, that have no unrighteouſneſſe in them, who are able Miniſters of the New Covenant, not of the Letter but of the Spirit, as it is written and the word of Faith in the Spirits Miniſtration, we own and honour in our ſouls, God is our Record that we lye not, but his Spirit witneſſeth with us in the ſame, who are ſealed and ſent, and are led by his Spirit, whereby we know that we are the Sons and the children of God, as it is written and witneſſed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14, 15, 16. <hi>John</hi> 7.16, 17, 18. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.6, 7, 8. <hi>John</hi> 3.31, 32, <hi>to the end. Rom.</hi> 10.13, 14, 15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.11, 12, 15, 16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.27. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</p>
            <p>But all hireling Prieſts that Preaches for hire, and beares rule by their meanes, as the falſe Prophets did, and as they do, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.10, 11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.30, 31. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. Such we deny, and againſt them reſtifie, and all that holds upon idols temple, and calls it a Church and ſpri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>es In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ts, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt nor his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles never practiſed any ſuch thing to ſuch objects, neither have they any Rule in the Scripture for it, ſuch we deny, and all that do things by imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Letter, and have not the life, and all that are called of men Maſters, and have the chiefeſt place in the idols temples, and ſuch as takes Tythes, who oppreſſe the creation thereby, ſuch are no Miniſters of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118674:5"/>Chriſt, but are Gentiles, and amongſt the Scribes and Phariſees, and ſuch we deny, and wo is their portion, therefore beware of all ſuch, <hi>Mark,</hi> 12.38, 39, 40. and <hi>Mark</hi> 10.42, 43, 44. <hi>Mathew</hi> 23, and all ſuch we deny, who have fellowſhip with devils, that eat and drink not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Lords body as the Gentiles do, and as it is written, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.29. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.20, 21.</p>
            <p>And all that takes Texts, and adds their own inventions, and ſpeaks the words of others, ſtealing the word from their neighbour, and ſpeaketh from the mouth of the Lord, and ſaith the Letter and the Spirit are inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, ſuch we deny, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18. <hi>Jer</hi> 23.29.30.31.32.</p>
            <p>And all that denyeth perfection by Chriſt in the New Covenant, and Goſpel Miniſtration, ſuch we deny, and witneſſe the New Covenant and the perfection, as it is written, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118674:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TRUTH</hi> Lifting up its head above Scandals. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.28. <hi>to the end. Rom.</hi> 2.5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</head>
            <head type="sub">Occaſioned at a Meeting at <hi>Harliſton</hi> in <hi>Stafforth</hi>-Shire, upon the <hi>4.</hi> day of the week, and the <hi>27.</hi> day of the <hi>7.</hi> month, between thoſe called Quakers, and the people of the water Baptiſme, or one called by the Name of <hi>Thomas Pallard,</hi> a teacher to that people, and one known to the world by the name of <hi>Richard Farnworth,</hi> whom they ſcornfully call a Quaker.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Homas Pallard,</hi> at the Meeting as aboveſaid, thou coming thither of purpoſe to cavill, to oppoſe the Truth that day, thou out of ſubtilty, and ſerpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine policy, when thou could not in honeſty object any thing againſt what was declared, yet out of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty thou queried concerning the New Covenant ſpoken of, that day, and asked, whether or no I lived in the injoyment of that Covenant ſpoken of, I anſwered and ſaid I did.</p>
            <p>Then thou <hi>Pallard</hi> ſaid, that in the tenor of the New Covenant, it was ſaid, according to the Fathers promiſe, that they in that Covenant ſhould be all taught of God, and he would be mercifull unto their ſins and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and remember them no more, and then it it was ſo, it might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that I was freed from ſin; and <hi>John</hi> ſaid, he that ſaid he had no ſin, he deceived himſelf, and the truth was not in him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118674:6"/>
Here out of ſubtilty thou went about to have had <hi>Johns</hi> words to have croſt the end of the New Covenant of grace, which is confirmed by an Oath of him that liveth for ever, for the Law made nothing perfect, but the bringing in of a better hope did, which hope is Chriſt as it is ſaid, the Myſtery and the hope of Glory, as it is written, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.3. verſe, and he that hath this hope purifieth himſelf even as he is pure, as <hi>Iohn</hi> hath ſaid, whoſe words thou would have had by thy craft, to have made void and null the Covenant of God, in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, which thou could not, for Chriſt Jeſus is the end of the one, and the beginning and fulfilling of the other, who took away the firſt, and did eſtabliſh the ſecond, and by one offering he hath for ever perfected them that are ſanctified, and their ſins and iniquiries will he remember no more, as he hath ſaid; and where remiſſion of ſins is, there is no more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for ſin, but there is boldneſſe to enter into the holieſt by the blood of Jeſus, by the new and living way which he hath conſecrated through the vail, that is to ſay his fleſh, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.9, 10, <hi>to the</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Pallard</hi> I asked thee, if <hi>Iohn</hi> when he ſpoke thoſe words did write thoſe words for a continuance in ſin, becauſe afterwards he ſaith, <hi>My little children, theſe things write I unto you that ye ſin not,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.1. And <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid afterwards, <hi>My little children I have written unto you becauſe your ſins are forgiven you for his Names ſake, and he that abideth in him ſinneth not, he that ſinneth hath neither ſeen him nor known him,</hi> as it is written 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.13 14. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.6, 7.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Iohn</hi> is ſpeaking of the two ſeeds, and the new birth, and the manifeſtations of the love of Chriſt, and the difference between the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and the wicked, or the children of God and the children of the devill, and as he cometh up to ſpeak of higher degrees in the grouth, he ſaith, <hi>He that is born of God ſinneth not, neither can he ſin becauſe he is born of God, and his ſeed remaineth in him, and he cannot ſin becauſe his ſeed remaineth in him;</hi> and he that is begotten of God keepeth himſelf, and the wicked one touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him not, as it is written, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3 9. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.18. And <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid, that <hi>he that commits ſin is of the devill,</hi> and he that ſinned not was of God, and thereby the children of God and the children of the divell was to be known aſunder, for the divels children ſinneth, and Gods children ſinneth not, as it is there ſaid, and Chriſt Jeſus was made manifeſt to take away their ſins, and in him was no ſin at all, and as he was, ſo was they then in that preſent world, as it is written and left upon record. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.14. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.27, 28. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.20. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.16, 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pallard,</hi> then thou told of a viſible Church, and viſible Officers, and viſible Ordinances, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſaid unto thee again, that the Church was in God, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, made all of living Stones, elect and precious, a ſpiritual houſe for God to dwell in, by the Spirit, and Officers and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers were made by the holy Ghoſt, and he is not viſible, for the world ſeeth him not, neither knoweth him, as it is written. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5, 6. <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.17.</p>
            <p>And God is a Spirit, and his Church is ſpirituall, and they endured as ſeeing him who is inviſible, and they were not come to the Mount which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118674:6"/>could be touched, but they was come to Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> and to the City of the living God, and to the heavenly Jeruſalem, which is inviſible, and to an innumerable company of Angels, and to the Generall Aſſembly and Church of the firſt born, written in heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the Spirits of juſt men made perfect, and that was not viſible, but inviſible, and incomprehenſible in the power and life of God the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22, 23.</p>
            <p>And Chriſt is the head of this ſpirituall body his Church, which he hath purchaſed with his blood, and he rules in it, and orders it by his Spirit, and he hath put all things under his feet, and given him to be head over all things to the Church, which is his body, the fulneſſe of him that filleth all in all, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1, 22, 23.</p>
            <p>And he came and preached peace to them that were a far off, and to them that were nigh, and he alſo preached to the Spirits in priſon, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3 19. And he is the ſame yeſterday, to day and for ever, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8. and the word of Faith is preached by the Righteouſneſſe of Faith in the heart by Chriſt Jeſus there, in his Church and Temple which is holy and pure: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>Rom</hi> 10.6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p>For through him we have an acceſſe to the Father by one Spirit, and are baptized by one Spirit, into one Body, which is Spirituall, and we are made to drink into one Spirit, where the fruit of the Vine is, and the bread of life, and the water of life, the thirſty ſouls for to refreſh, and there is one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme, one God, and Father of us all, who are heirs according to the promiſe, and being baptized into Chriſt, we have put on Chriſt, and are fellow-Citizens with the Saints, and of the houſhold of God, and are built upon the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Prophets and Apoſtles, Chriſt Jeſus being the chief corner Stone, in whom all the building fitly framed, groweth unto an holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Lord, in whom alſo we are builded together for an habitation of God through the Spirit; and God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth, and the Church is in God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12, 13. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27, 28, 29. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.18. <hi>to the end. Iohn</hi> 6. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.23, 24. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.1. <hi>verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then I asked thee <hi>Thomas Pallard</hi> water Baptizer, if God who was a Spirit was viſible, for the Church is in him, the Pillar and Ground of all Truth, and the Word and the Law and the Ordinances and Oracles of God ſtands in the incomprehenſibleneſſe of his infiniteneſſe, and his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is in the Spirit and power of the holy Ghoſt in the eternity and the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Scripture, or the Divine Epiſtles written by the Spirit is in the heart tables as it is written, not with ink but with the Spirit of the living God in the myſtery, and the Baptiſme is in the Spirit, and praying and ſinging and preaching is in the power, and pure and eternall wiſdome by the Spirit, and the watch is in the Spirit, and all the officers and overſeers in the Church of Chriſt, is in the Spirit made by the power and authority of the holy Ghoſt in the blood of Chriſt, ſealed by the Spirit, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, and Chriſt is the chief Shepherd and Biſhop of the ſoul, and maketh his Angels Spirits, and his Miniſters flames of fire, and they are not of the Letter but of the Spirit, not made by the will of man, but by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118674:7"/>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ill of God, which is ſanctification, and <hi>Paul</hi> was made a Miniſter of the New Covenant, in the Goſpel Miniſtration, not by the will of man but by the will of God, and by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, as he cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified to the brethren by the Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.11, 12, and Chriſt was reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15, 16, and he did preach Chriſt by the Spirit in them that he preached unto, and they were able Miniſters, not of the Letter but of the Spirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5, 6, 7. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.25, 26, 27. and 28. 2 <hi>Cor,</hi> 3. to the 7, verſe.</p>
            <p>And thou <hi>Pallard,</hi> who art a great teacher to the baptized people, at that time ſaid, that the Spirit and the Letter were inſeparable, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Herein thou openly laid out thy ignorance of God, and of Chriſt and the Spirit and the Goſpel, and the New Covenant, and thy nakedneſs is bare, thy covers will not hide thee, to ſay the Letter and the Spirit is inſeparable: God is a Spirit, but God is not the Letter, neither is the Letter God; Chriſt is the New Covenant, but Chriſt is not the Letter, neither is the Letter Chriſt, and the Goſpel is the power of God unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but the Letter is neither the Goſpel nor the power, but declareth of it, and if our Goſpel be hid, it is hid to them that are loſt, in whom the God of this world hath blinded their mindes, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3, 4. But the Letter is not hid, it is open to all, to read, or get read, but the Goſpel is yet hid to thee <hi>Pallard,</hi> and all in thy nature, and thou haſt made thy ſelf a Miniſter of the Letter by thy own will, and never was made a Miniſter of the Goſpel of grace, nor of the New Covenant yet in the blood or life of Jeſus, according to the will of God the Father, that ſaith the Letter and the Spirit are one, and inſeparable, as if the Spirit of God were lockt up and confined in the Letter, which is death, and if ſo, all the world would have the Spirit, and buy and ſell it, if it were in the Letter, and at an eaſie rate, they might buy it for three or four ſhillings, for ſo may they buy the Letter, but the Spirit cannot be bought, therefore it is not in the Letter; if that the Spirit had been ſo eaſily come to, or if it could have been bought, <hi>Simon Magus</hi> proffered money for it, but could not thereby gain it: And when he ſaw that through laying on of the Apoſtles hands the holy Ghoſt was given; he offered them mony for it; now the holy Ghoſt is not in the Letter, but the Holy Ghoſt is the Spirit of God, in the Bloud or Life of Chriſt: but the Letter is not the Spirit Printed in Paper, and bound up in Lether, that a man may carry it in his hand or pocket, and buy it and ſell it for mony, ſo can he not do the holy Ghoſt &amp; many may be baptized with water, and want the Spirit as thou doſt, and many of you water baptizers do, that as yet knowes no holy Ghoſt, that ſayes the Letter and the Spirit are inſeparable, there you water Baptizers are out of the Doctrine and life of the Apoſtles, and they that baptized with water, who had power to give the holy Ghoſt, which you have not, Read <hi>Acts</hi> 8.12. to the 18.</p>
            <p>And when <hi>Simon</hi> ſaw, that through the laying on of the Apoſtles hands the holy Ghoſt was given, he offered them mony, ſaying, Give me alſo that power; <hi>Simon</hi> did acknowledge the holy Ghoſt to be the power, and not the Letter, here he was beyond you, but becauſe the Spirit and Power is ſeparated from the Letter, <hi>Simons</hi> money and he was like to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, that thought to have bought the Spirit and power of God, had
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118674:7"/>it been in the Letter he might have bought and ſold it, but he could not attain to it, and all that trades with the Letter are as ignorant of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as <hi>Simon</hi> was, and all that thinks to buy it for money, and raiſe the Spirit out of the Letter, are ſorcerers, and in nature like to <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> and <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer ſpoken of in Scripture, that were in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles times, and now there are many <hi>Maguſes</hi> and <hi>Elimaſes</hi> without the Spirit, and hath the Letter, but labours to keep people out of the Faith and power of Truth, and ſeeks to ſhut up the Kingdome of Heaven from men, as the Phariſees did, and keep people in outſide formes, without the holy Ghoſt, or the Power, as thou <hi>Pallard</hi> and all in that nature doth, that ſaith, the Letter and the Spirit are inſeparable; there thou art out of the Faith, and out of the power of the Spirit, and wants the holy Ghoſt, and art in that generation which had the Letter, but perſecuted the Spirit and art baptized, but wants the holy Ghoſt, as <hi>Simon</hi> did, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.18, 19, to the 24. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.6, 7, 8, to the 11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.12, 13, 15, 25, 28, 33.</p>
            <p>And thou <hi>Pallard,</hi> when thou ſtood to oppoſe the truth, and to keep people out of the Faith, in a dead water form, which neither waſheth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, nor cleanſeth from ſin, as thou ſaid, yet <hi>Elimas</hi>-like thou would with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Trnth, and laboured to keep out of the Faith with thy ſorceries, and ſaid that the Letter and the Spirit was inſeparable, but thou herein was nakedly ſeen, inſomuch that the people many of them would not be deluded by thee, but cryed out of thy folly, as they might well, that ſaid the Letter and the Spirit were inſeparable, then ſaid the people, if ſo, the Spirit might be bought for three or four ſhillings, and many would have the Spirit, for they might buy a Bible for 3 or 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> Here <hi>Pallard,</hi> thou great water Baptizer, thy folly did exceedingly appear, and thy ignorance of God and the Spirit was thereby diſcovered, and that thou art a meer formall hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, in the form and the Letter without the Spirit; and here I charge thee in the preſence of the Lord to be no Miniſter of Chriſt, nor the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, nor of the New Covenant, but without the Spirit, and knowes not the power nor the holy Ghoſt, and thou and all in thy nature hath no more power to lay on hands than <hi>Simon Magus</hi> had, who was baptized in the water, but had not the holy Ghoſt, and thy laying on of hands will work no more effect than <hi>Simons</hi> would have done; for the power thou haſt not, nor none in thy nature, that ſaith the Letter and the Spirit are inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable, and thou art no miniſter of the Spirit, but of the Letter, and ran, but never was ſent of the Lord, therefore he is againſt thee, and all in thy nature, that ſteals words from others to ſpeak, as the falſe Prophets did, read <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.21, 22, 30, 31, 2. <hi>verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou <hi>Pallard</hi> water Baptizer, that art a Miniſter of the Letter, and not the Spirit, that ſaith the Spirit and the Letter are one, or inſeparable thou art contrary to the Miniſters of Chriſt, and the New Covenant in the Goſpel miniſtration, who were able Miniſters of the Spirit, and not of the Letter: for the Letter is death, but the Spirit is life, and is out of the Letter, and in the new Covenant, annointed and ſealed are they that are ſent, and preaches the Spirit and not the Letter. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.20; 27. <hi>John</hi> 3.33, 34. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</p>
            <p>Here thou art ſhut out of the annointing, and out of the new Covenant
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118674:8"/>and out of the Spirit, and ſo are all in thy nature, and are in darkneſſe and death, unſent, and unſealed, and not annointed, no Miniſters of the life nor the Spirit, but of death and darkneſſe, and in the oldneſſe of the Letter, and not in the newneſſ of the Spirit, and there you are ſeparated from the life of Truth, and in the ſelf ſeparation, who have not the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that ſay the Letter is the Spirit, or the Letter and the Spirit is one, and cannot be ſeparated, but the Miniſters of Chriſt were not of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but out of the ſelf-ſeparation, and in the Spirit, and had the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit, and the gifts given to profit withall, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. and they did not then ſerve in the oldneſſe of the Letter, as you Baptiſts do, but their ſervice ſtood in the life and power of Truth, and in newneſſe of the Spirit, and not in the Letter: neither was their preaching with the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticing words of mans wiſdom as yours is, but with demonſtration of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and in power, that the Faith of others might ſtand out of the wiſdom or policy of man, in the power wiſdome and ſtrength perfection and power of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4, 5. 1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 1.30, 31. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.6, verſes.</p>
            <p>And Miniſters of the new Covenant in the power and life of Truth were Divine Epiſtles written in the Tables of the heart, written not with ink as the Letter is, but their Divine writings in the heart tables, were by the Spirit of God both written and miniſtred out from the Spirit, and not from the Letter, as it is ſaid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>And here thou <hi>Pallard,</hi> and all in thy nature, are razed out of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, and out of their Divine Epiſtles, and out of their life, and art in the Letter, as the falſe conceited Jews was without the Word of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, that lived by their thoughts and conceits then, as you Baptiſts do now, and Jeſus Chriſt ſaid unto them, <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them ye think ye have eternall life, and they are they that do teſtifie of me; I am the life, and ye will not come unto me that ye might have life;</hi> ſee <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.39, 40.</p>
            <p>The Jew outwardly which put Chriſt to death had the Letter, but not the ſpirit, nor the life, and there they was ſeparated from the ſpirit and the life, and the love of God was not in them, but they had great knowledge of the Letter without them. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.40, 41, 42. <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.4, 5, 6.</p>
            <p>And thou <hi>Pallard</hi> art amongſt the outward Jews, and all in thy nature without the love of God as they was, and oppoſeth the Truth as they did, and hath knowledge in the Letter as they had, but are without the ſpirit, and the power of the holy Ghoſt as they was, and the Letter is thy life, and thou wilt not come out of it to Chriſt, who is the eternall life, who thy ſelf art in death and darkneſſe, that ſaith the Letter and the ſpirit are inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable and afterwards ſayes ignorantly that it is a Hiſtory, and the Spirit is to thee a myſtery, that art ſo in confuſion, and in Egypt and Babylon, building up and throwing down, and deluding the people there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; for ſhame, bluſh, and give over deceiving the people, and all ſuch as thou art, who hath the Letter, but not the ſpirit, that ſaith the ſpirit and the Letter is one and cannot be divided nor ſeparated, and yet calleth it a Hiſtory, when the Scripture ſaith, Chriſt is a Myſtery, then not a hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; therefore ſilence deceit, and ſtop your mouths, your blackneſſe and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118674:8"/>darkneſſe is ſeen, and your deeds are for condemnation with the light, that are acted in that nature, contrary to the light: <hi>John</hi> 3.19, 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pallard</hi> thou art ignorant of God, and all in thy nature, that ſaith the Letter and the Spirit are inſeparable, for God is a Spirit, but God is not the Letter, the Word of God is eternall life, and doth endure for ever, this is the record that God hath given to us even eternal life, and this life is in his Son, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.10, 11. and not in the Letter; and we know that the ſon of God is come, &amp; hath given us an underſtanding that we may know him that is true and we are in him that is true, not in the Letter which is death, but in the ſon which is life, even in his ſon Jeſus Chriſt, this is true God and life eternall, and the Word of God is eternall life, which doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for ever: 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.12, 18, 20. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22, 23.</p>
            <p>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God, all things were made by him, and without him was not any thing made that was made, in him was life, and the life was the Light of men, &amp;c. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>The Word is God, but the Letter is not God, neither were all things made by the Letter, but all things were made by the Word, therefore the Spirit which is the Word of God: <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.17. is not the Letter: The Word is within in the heart, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.6, 7, 8. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.14. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. but the Letter is without, bound up in Paper and ink, which declares of of the Word.</p>
            <p>The Word is the life of the world, and the Word ſanctifieth ſoul and body, as it is ſaid, ſanctifie them with thy Word, but it is not ſaid, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie them with the Letter, and ſo we were waſhed, cleanſed, juſtified, and ſanctified in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.16, 17, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Iohn</hi> 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.12.</p>
            <p>But Letter doth not ſanctifie, neither is the Letter the Light and life of ſanctified men, but the Word and the Spirit is, which is not the Letter.</p>
            <p>And all things are upheld by the Word of his power, <hi>Hebrews</hi> the 1. But all things are not upheld by the Letter.</p>
            <p>See how dark and ignorant of God art thou <hi>Pallard;</hi> for the Word of God is as a fire, and a hammer, and breaketh the Rocks to pieces, <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.29. but the Letter doth not, and the Word of the Lord is as a fire in the bones, <hi>Ier.</hi> 20.9. but the letter is not; by the Word of the Lord were the heavens made, and all the hoſt of them, by the Breath of his mouth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.6. but by the Letter they were not; the Word of the Lord is for ever ſettled in heaven, ſo is not the Letter, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119 89. His name is called the Word of God: <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13: But his Name is not the Letter: <hi>Pallard</hi> how dark art thou, that ſayes the Letter and the Spirit are inſeparable; and then after called it a Hiſtory, is the Spirit of God a Hiſtory? and is Chriſt a Hiſtory? The declaration, ſaith he, is a Miſtery; but I bade thee inſtance one place where the Bible was called a Hiſtory, but thou could not: ſee how confuſed thou art, and how blinde, <hi>and if the blinde lead the blinde, ſhall not both fall into the ditch?</hi> Here I charge thee to be ignorant of God, and ignorant of his teachings: And I charge thee to be no Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Chriſt, nor the Goſpel, that ſayes the Letter and the Spirit are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable; thou haſt ſet up thy ſelf to be a Teacher of others, and many
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118674:9"/>ſuch as thou art, who art yet untaught of God, and you would be teachers of others, before you be taught to deny your ſelves, and thou, and all that ſayes the Spirit and the Letter are inſeparable, and cals it a Hiſtory, you are blind and ignorant of the Miſtery, and blinde and ignorant of the truth, and the power of God you know not, nor the holy Ghoſt, that preaches the Letter without the Spirit, and would raiſe up the ſpirit out of the dead Letter, all ſuch are witches. Sorcerers, and conjurers; and we hold all ſuch accurſed: <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles of Chriſt went up and down preaching the Kingdom, and preaching the Word, and not the Letter, and the Word grew and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed, but the Letter did not grow and multiply, <hi>Acts</hi> 12 24. And they were ſent out to preach by the Spirit, but they were not ſent out to preach by the Letter; and the Spirit of Chriſt doth quicken the mortall body, but the Letter doth not, but the Letter doth not, and by the Spirit Chriſt were raiſed from the dead, but by the Letter he were not raiſed from the dead; <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was annointed to preach by the Spirit, but the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hath not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to annoint withall; he ſaid, the Lord God and his Spirit had ſent him, but he did not ſay the Letter ſent him, neither did he ask leave of the Letter, when the Spirit ſaid go, and all the Apoſtles were ſent by the Spirit in the power of the holy Ghoſt, but they was not ſent by the Letter, which is neither Spirit power nor holy Ghoſt; and the Spirit of the Lord bade <hi>Philip</hi> joyn himſelf to the Eunuchs chariot, but the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter did not, the Eunuch had the Letter to read, but knew not the guide which is the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14. and the Spirit of the Lord caught away <hi>Philip</hi> again, that the Eunuch ſaw him no more, but the Letter did not: <hi>Acts</hi> 8.29, <hi>and</hi> 39. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61. <hi>Luk</hi> 4.18. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.8. And the Spirit it ſelf beareth witneſſe with our Spirits that we are the children of God, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.24 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pallard,</hi> thou water Baptizer, and all you Water Baptizers, that ſay the Letter and the Spirit is one, or inſeparable, here your ignorance of God and Chriſt and the Spirit is ſeen, that you have the Letter but not the Spirit, and ſtands in need to be taught what be the firſt Principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, though you take upon you to be teachers of others, you are yet dull of hearing, and knoweth neither the power, ſpirit, nor holy Ghoſt, Church Faith, hope, election, overſeers made by the holy Ghoſt, nor the annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, nor yet the true fear, that ſaith the Letter and the Spirit are inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and is a Hiſtory, as thou <hi>Pallard</hi> ſaid, who alſo ſaid, that judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was not committed to Chriſt, whileſt he were in the world, and Chriſt himſelf ſaid, that for judgement was he come into the world, that they that ſaw not might ſee, and that they that ſaw might be made blinde, <hi>John</hi> 9.39.</p>
            <p>And thou here would make Chriſt a lyer, that ſaith he had not judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment committed to him whileſt he was in the world, and he ſaid, for judgement he came into the world, but thou that ſayes thou ſees, art now ſound blinde and ignorant of the Myſtery, that ſaith the Letter and the Spirit are inſeparable, and calls it a Hiſtory, but thou are found the lyer, and the Antichriſt, and knowes not the Spirit, who are not in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, of Chriſt and ſo hath not God, 2 <hi>Iohn</hi> 9: and thou lyer, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118674:9"/>all lyars are for the lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15. <hi>Rev</hi> 21.27. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.8.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Pallard</hi> ſtop thy mouth, and all in thy nature, who are out of the Light, and out of the Truth, and ſilence deceit, I charge thee in the preſence of the Lord, as I ſaid to thee when thou went forth, to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from that place, for I ſhall be a witneſſe for the truth, againſt thee and thy deceit, before the judgement ſeat of Chriſt, and to that in thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall I be witneſſed which doth convince thee of ſin, and check and reprove thee in ſecret; thou ſaid three times that <hi>I</hi> denyed the Scriptures to manifeſt thy lyes, when it was proved by the Scriptures, and witneſſed to the contrary there, evidently before thy eyes, as many can witneſſe, and that within thy conſcience will witneſſe the ſame, that which reproves thee for ſin and evill, and checks thee in ſecret, which lets thee ſee the deceit of thy heart, and maketh manifeſt ſubtilty and craft, which is acted in that nature contrary to the light, but the Lord taketh the wiſe in their own craftineſſe, as it is written, and ſo was thou taken in thy ſnare thy ſelf, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thy water-baptiſme, that thou could not get looſe, though thou make it thy idoll which thou ſo much takes pleaſure in, but thy image would not abide the fire and the hammer at that time, but was ready to break all in pleces; but thy works, and every mans works in thy nature ſhall be tryed by fire, and all that will not abide the fire ſhall be burnt; for every mans works ſhall be made manifeſt, whether it be ſilver, gold, precious ſtones, wood, hay, or ſtubble that he buildeth for the day ſhal declare it, becauſe it ſhall be revealed by fire, and the fire ſhall try every mans works of what ſort it is, and his works that will not abide the fire muſt be burnt, and he himſelf ſuffer loſſe, as thou art like to do, and all in thy nature, for the wiſedome of this world is fooliſhneſſe with God; for it is written, he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the wiſe in their own craftineſſe, as thou waſt taken in thine, and thy Babyloniſh building is known, with the Light it is ſeen and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and with the Light to be condemned, and if any of thoſe builders in thy nature be ſaved, it muſt be ſo as by fire: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12, 13, 14, 15 and 19. and 20.</p>
            <p>Thou couldeſt not witneſſe that thy water baptiſme did waſh away ſin, neither couldeſt thou witneſſe that thy ſins were waſht away by it, but were in confuſion and lyes, ſaying and unſaying, Babyloniſh, building up, and throwing down, and daubing with untempered morter, as all in thy nature do, neither couldeſt thou witneſſe the gift of the holy Ghoſt, that it were or could be given by any of you water baptizers, when it were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of thee upon thy examination in that thing at that time, as many can witneſſe, and that in thy conſcience ſhall witneſſe the ſame, the Light of Chriſt Jeſus which will condemn thee, and all that hate it, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it; for this is the condemnation of the world, that light is come into the world, and men love darkneſſe rather than light, and the reaſon is, becauſe their deeds are evill, as thine is: <hi>John</hi> 3.19, 20.</p>
            <p>And as thou could not witneſſe to the waſhing away of ſin by your water Baptiſme, nor the gift of the holy Ghoſt to be given by it, when it was demanded of thee, neither couldeſt thou witneſſe to the eternall judgment, and alſo denyed perfection to be attainable; and here thou, and all you
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118674:10"/>water baptizers are razed out of the Apoſtles doctrine and life, who ſaid, that they would leave the firſt Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and go on to perfection; which you Baptiſts, and thou <hi>Pallard,</hi> great wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Baptizer, denies, and ſo denyes that which is the whole life of truth, and the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt, and they that had paſſed thorough the Doctrine of Baptiſmes, and the laying on of hands, they paſſed on to the Reſurrection, and to eternall judgement, which thou <hi>Pallard</hi> denyes, for they came to the Generall Aſſembly and church of the firſt born, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the Spirits of juſt men made perfect, and to Jeſus the Mediator of the New Covenant, and they knew the ſhakings, not of the earth onely, but of the heavens alſo, that things which could not be ſhaken might remain, which ſhakings thou knows nothing of, nor none in thy nature, that denyes perfection, and the eternall judgement, but we having received a Kingdom which cannot be moved, have received grace whereby we may ſerve God acceptably with reverence and godly fear; for our God is a conſuming fire, the ſame that theirs was that left the firſt Principles of the Doctrines of Baptiſmes, and the laying on of hands, and the Reſurrection of the dead, and came to the eternall judgement, and to God the judge of all, and to the Spirits of juſt men made perfect, and were in the Church of the firſt born, written in heaven, and had received the Kingdom, and know the conſuming fire, and dwelt with everlaſting burnings, and this I witneſſe, he that can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it let him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2, 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22. to the end. <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 40.28, 29, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 33.14, 15, 16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to thee <hi>Pallard,</hi> great water Baptizer, this is a miſtery, and to all in thy nature, that denyes the eternall judgement, and the firſt Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and the perfection which the Saints witneſſed, and they were ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen with Chriſt, and were made to ſit together with him in heavenly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſaid to others in their grouh, If ye he riſen with Chriſt, ſet your affections on things which are above, and not on things which are on the earth, and ſome ſaid, that their converſation were in heaven, and others knew that ſo many of them as were Baptized into Chriſt, were baptized into his death, that like as Chriſt was raiſed from the dead by the glory of the Father, even ſo they alſo ſhould walk in newneſſe of life, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.4, 5, 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1, 2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20, 21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.1, 2, 3. <hi>to the</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>But thou, and you water baptizers are yet in the oldneſſe of the Letter, and not in the baptiſme of ſufferings, nor in the new life, nor knowes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the eternall Judgement, nor of the Reſurrection, nor perfection, nor the New Covenant, nor the Seal thereof, that ſayes the Bible is a Hiſtory, and the Spirit and the Letter are inſeparable, as thou <hi>Pallard,</hi> great waterman did; and thou, and the other that were with thee at that, time, impudently did lye before the people, and ſaid, Chriſt had not judgement committed to him whiloſt he were in the world, and Chriſt himſelf ſaid, for that cauſe was he come into the world, as I then told thee, and as thou mayeſt ſee in <hi>John</hi> 9.39. And where he ſaid to the Jews that they judged him after the fleſh, but he judged no man after the fleſh, but he judged righteouſly, and with righteous judgement, and his judgement
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118674:10"/>was true, for he and his Father was one, as he there ſaid, and he was one that bore witneſſe of himſelf, and the Father that ſent him bare witneſs with him, and Chriſt there had judgment with the Father, and all judgment he ſaid were committed to him; and he told them (the envious Jews) that they were of their father the devill, and his works they would do, and he told them there was no truth in them, for their father the devill had not abode in the Truth, and they was of him, and he told them he knew that they had not the love of God in them, and his judgement was true, and he called them ſerpents and vipers, and ſaid, How-ſhould they eſcape the damnation of hell, and he pronounced woes to Phariſees and Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites then, ſuch as had a form from the Letter, but was ſeparated from the Spirit and life of what they did profeſſe, and from Chriſt and the new Covenant, and were in the Letter without the Spirit, as you Baptizers are and as thou <hi>Pallard</hi> art, and all that are in their nature, and ſuch as ſay the Bible is a Hiſtory, and the Spirit and the Letter is inſeparable, and that ſayes, Chriſt had not judgement committed to him whileſt he were in the world, as you Baptiſts, and thou <hi>Pallard</hi> did, here I charge thee in the preſence of the Lord, and all in thy nature to be falſe accuſers of Chriſt, and lyers and enemies of his truth, as the envious Jews was, as thou <hi>Pallard</hi> art, and all you who are in their nature, and as you may read, <hi>John</hi> 8.44. <hi>John.</hi> 5.39, 40, 41; <hi>&amp;c. Mat.</hi> 23.33.</p>
            <p>Thou may well take upon thee <hi>Pallard</hi> to lye of me and the truth, that would ſo impudently lye of Chriſt, that ſaid he had not judgement com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him, nor given him whilſt he was in the world, when he ſaid, that for judgment he was come into the world, as I then told thee: And ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ſaid, that he had life in himſelf as the Father had, and he had autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity given him to execute judgement, as it is written, and as he was come for Judgement into the world, and had authority given him to execute it: So thirdly, he had power to quicken whom he would, as well as the Father, and he ſaid, that the Father had committed all judgement unto him, <hi>John</hi> 9.39. <hi>John</hi> 5.21. <hi>to the</hi> 28.</p>
            <p>And thou that ſaid the Bible was a Hiſtory, and yet the Letter and the Spirit is inſeparable, and that Chriſt had not judgment committed to him whileſt he was in the world, and that Chriſt had not Judgement commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him; for he had a body, and were ſenſible of hunger, and ſuch ſtuffe thou had, and were in the lyes, blaſphemies, and falſe accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as thy fruits made thee manifeſt, yet thou takes upon thee to teach and baptize, and art of great account amongſt poor ſeduced water bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized people; but thou art diſcovered to thy ſhame, and it may be for the good of many poor ſouls to ſee your deceits come to light. Oh, thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull one, be aſhamed and confounded, let ſhame cover thy face, repent and give over deceiving the people, and all in thy nature, now thou art warned, as thou was then, and to the Light of God in thy conſcience am I made manifeſt, and that will witneſſe for me and the Truth, againſt thee and thy deceit before the Judgement Seat of Chriſt, in the great day of the Lord, when I ſhall alſo ſtand before the Judgement Seat, and be a witneſſe againſt thee there, except thou repent of thy lyes and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and falſe accuſations, and deny them all openly, as thou witneſſed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118674:11"/>to them openly, and now to the Light in thy conſcience ſhall this be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, which light will be thy eternall condemnation, if thou hate it, and act knowingly and wilfully contrary to it; now thou haſt time, prize it, for one wo is paſt, but behold two woes more followeth after, as it is written; <hi>And the ſixth Angel ſounded, and I heard a voice from the four hornes of the golden Alter, which is before God, ſaying to the ſixth Angel which had the Trumpet, looſe the four Angels which are bound in the great river Euphrates, and the four Angels were looſed which were prepared, for an hour and a day and a month and a year, for to ſlay the third part of men; he that both an car to hear let him hear,</hi> and he that can receive it, let him receive it: <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.12, 13, 14, 15 <hi>Zech</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>Therefore now <hi>Pallard,</hi> great water Baptizer, and all that are as thou art, teachers of others before they be taught themſelves, and all imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that worſhips ye know not what, who are dipt In the water, but are ignorant of the Divine nature, that ſayes the Bible is a Hiſtory, and yet the Letter and the Spirit, <hi>Pallard,</hi> thou ſayes are one and inſeparable; how blinde and ignorant art thou, and are you Baptizers of the Miſtery, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence all fleſh, and ſtop your mouths, and take heed of deluding poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple any longer, I warn you, and charge you, in the preſence of the Lord, as you will anſwer it, before the Judgement ſeat of the great God, and <hi>Pallard,</hi> that in thy conſcience ſhall be a witneſſe for me, when thou ſees me not, the Light of Chriſt Jeſus there, for to that am I made manifeſt, yet ſhut up from thy dark minde, for Light ſhines in darkneſſe, but dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe comprehendeth it not, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9,</p>
            <p>Yet Light comprehendeth darkneſſe, though darkneſſe cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Light, and with the Light that comprehends the world art thou comprehended, and with the Light which changeth not art thou ſeen, and all in thy nature, and known to be our of the Light, and out of the Truth, and out of the new Covenant, and out of the Church that is in God the firſt-born which is written in heaven, and no officer there, nor no Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the new Covenant and the Spirit, nor yet baptized into Chriſt, nor no friend of Chriſt, nor none in thy nature, no more than the envious Jews and the Phariſees was, and the Prieſts; the Prieſts of the world and thou art in one nature, and guided by one ſpirit, the ſame that guides all the children of diſobedience, as it doth you, and there is no difference between them and you, but that you have the ſheeps cloathing, and they have the wolves, but both one inſide, and nature; thou haſt the outſide form according to the Letter more than they have, but thou art without the power, and ignorant of the Miſtery in the Spiritas they are, and as above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, that ſayes the Bible is the Hiſtory in the Letter, and yet thou ſayes the roughneſſe is felt, and thy darkneſſe is ſeen, thou dark Sott, would thou bring God and Chriſt, Faith, hope, Election, and the New Covenant, the holy Ghoſt, and the eternall Spirit and bloud of the Covenant, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of death, and have them hiſtoricall, that ſayes the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures or Letter of the Bible is a Hiſtory, and the Spirit and the Letter are inſeparable, when as I told thee a Hiſtory was a fable or a ſtory, but the Scriptures I own to be a true Declaration of the Truth that they lived in that ſpoke them forth; and the Declaration of the Truth is moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118674:11"/>believed amongſt us that the world ſcornfully cals Quakers, and the life of them enjoyed, Chriſt Jeſus the chief ſhepherd and Biſhop of our ſouls; and though the Scriptures outwardly be not the Spirit nor the eternall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Word, nor the life of God and Chriſt and the Saints, yet the Scriptures are a true Declaration of thoſe things declared of, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.1. but not the Word of God, for it is eternall life, and liveth and endureth for ever: 1 <hi>John</hi> 2, 3.4, 5. 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.22.23.</p>
            <p>I would have had thee <hi>Pallard,</hi> to have proved by the Scripture that it was any where called a Hiſtory, and that the Spirit of God was kept or confined in a hiſtory or a fable, but thou could not, for godlineſſe is a miſtery, and the Devine Writings by the Spirit are in the new heart tables, as it is written, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.2, 3. and the Saints knowes Chriſt in them, and the opening of the Miſtery, and his Miniſters preaches him amongſt the Gentiles now; for you ſelf-conceated ones, like the outward Jews, will none of his counſel; but great is the miſtery of godlineſſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. and the Comforter that abideth for ever, even the Spirit of Truth, whom the world cannot receive; and you Phariſees and ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited ones cannot receive it, neither do you know him, that ſayes the Spirit is in the Letter, and the Letter is a Hiſtory, but we know him in the miſtery, and the Spirit of Truth to be out of a Hiſtory, for he dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in us, as ſaith the Scripture, <hi>John</hi> 14.15, 16, 17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.10, 11. Praiſed be the Lord for the riches of his love to our ſouls, in taking of the Seals, and opening the miſtery in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.11. <hi>to the end. Col,</hi> 1.25, 26, 27, 28.</p>
            <p>Which miſtery is yet hid to thee <hi>Pallard,</hi> water-Baptizer, and all in thy nature, that ſayes the Spirit and the Letter is inſeparable, and is a Hiſtory; ſtop thy mouth for ſhame, and cover thy lips, for the promiſe is not to that ſeed of the ſerpent which you wiſe ones of the world are one with, as the Phariſees and the envious Jews was; but the promiſe is to the ſeed of Abraham, according to the Spirit. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3, 29. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.28, 29.</p>
            <p>But as it was then, ſo it is now, they that are after the fleſh perſecute them that are after the Spirit, who are of that ſeed, yet we preach Chriſt crucified unto you ſelf-conceated ones, and outward Jews a ſtumbling block; and unto the Greeks fooliſhneſſe, but unto them that are of the ſeed according to the promiſe, and are for ſalvation, Chriſt the wiſdome of God and power of God; for Chriſt hath not ſent us to baptize with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but to preach to the Spirits in priſon, as he did, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18, 19. to the end, and not to preach the Goſpel with the enticing words of mans wiſdome, leſt the croſſe of Chriſt ſhould be of none effect, which is of great effect unto us, and to all that are ſubject unto it; for therein is our glorying in the Croſſe, by which we are crucified unto the world, and the world is by it crucified unto us, and we are crucified with Chriſt, yet we live but our life is in him, and by the Croſſe we live in him, and that he might reconcile both unto God in one body by the Croſſe having thereby ſlain the enmity, he came and preached peace to them that were a farre off, and to them that were nigh, for by the Croſſe through him we have an acceſſe by one Spirit unto the Father; and God forbid that we ſhould glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118674:12"/>in any thing ſave in the Croſſe of Chriſt, by which we are dead, and crucified to the world, and the world unto us: for in Chriſt Jeſus there is not any thing that availeth but a new Creature, and as many as walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Rule, peace be on them, and mercy, and upon the ſeed and Iſrael of God, for in him ſhall all the ſeed of Iſrael be juſtified, and ſhall glory through the Croſſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14, 15, 16. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.24 25. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.16, 17, 18.</p>
            <p>And the preaching of the Croſſe is to them that periſh fooliſhneſſe, for it is written, I will deſtroy the wiſedome of the wiſe, and bring to naught the councel of the prudent, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.11. to the 18. and in that day the deaf ſhall hear the words of the Book, which neither the learned nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned outwardly could open, and in that day of the opening of the Book or miſtery of godlineſſe, the eyes of the blinde ſhall ſee out of obſcurity and out of darkneſſe, and the meek who are of the righteous ſeed ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their joy in the Lord, and the poor among men ſhall rejoice in the holy one of Iſrael, for by the Croſſe which crucifies the world, and ſlayes the enmity therein, will the terrible one be cut off, and by the Croſſe will the ſcorner be conſumed, and by the Croſſe will all that watch for iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be ſlain, and cut down, therefore thus ſaith the Lord who redeemed <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> concerning the houſe of <hi>Iacob, Iacob</hi> ſhall not now be aſhamed, neither ſhall his face now wax pale; but when he ſees his children the work of mine hands in the midſt of him, they ſhall ſanctifie my Name, and ſanctifie the holy One of <hi>Iacob,</hi> who are of that ſeed, and ſhall fear the Lord God of Iſrael, and they alſo that erred in Spirit ſhall come to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and they that murmured ſhall learn Doctrine, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.18, 19. to the end.</p>
            <p>Where then is the wiſe? where is the Scribe, where is the diſputer of this world? Therefore, thus ſaith the Lord, I will proceed to do a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous work amongſt this people, ſuch as are of the wiſdome of the fleſh, and the ſeed of the ſerpent, whoſe hearts are removed from the Lord into the things of the world, and the earthly learning and knowledge, and the earthly part is above the good ſeed, and they draw near the Lord with their mouthes and their lips, but hearts are farre off, and their fear towards me ſaith the Lord, is taught by the Precepts of men; therefore the marvelous work that the Lord works amongſt them is this, the wiſdom of the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſe men ſhall periſh, and the underſtanding of the prudent in that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhall be hid, which is a work of wonder, for it is written, hath not not God made fooliſh the wiſdome of this world? For after, that in the wiſdom of God, the world by wiſdom knew not God, then after by the fooliſhneſſe of preaching it pleaſed God to ſave ſome, and the preaching of the Croſſe to the cutting down of the carnall part, and the raiſing up of the ſeed, and letting it out of Priſon by the power of the Lord, is now the ſame in the Miniſtery by the Spirit that it was then, for it doth now pleaſe God by the preaching of the croſs, which is counted fooliſhnes with world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſe men to ſave ſome, as he did then; For now the Jews require a ſign, and the greeks ſeek after worldly wiſdome, but we preach Chriſt crucified unto the Jews a ſtumbling block now, and unto the greeks fooliſhneſſe, as it was then amongſt the great outward Scholers and worldly wiſe men,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118674:12"/>And we ſee and know our Calling that are ſent to Preach and miniſter in the Croſſe, that thereby the enmity may be ſlain, and the ſeed be brought forth of priſon and bondage by the Croſſe again, for not many wiſe men, after the fleſh not many mighty, nor noble in the world, not many of them are called.</p>
            <p>Oh, how hard a thing it is for them that have riches to enter, becauſe of the Croſſe, but God hath choſen the fooliſh; poor, baſe, weak things in the worlds account as he did then, to preach the Croſſe, and to confound things that are mighty in the worlds eyes and account, as <hi>Pallard</hi> the great water Baptizer was; and things which are deſpiſed hath God choſen, and things which are not accounted of by the world, to bring to nought things that are of great account by them, that all fleſh may be ſilent, and not glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in his preſence.</p>
            <p>But in the Lord are the ſeed of Iſrael juſtified, and in him they glory, and he is made unto us wiſedome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification and redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, that according as it is written, he that glorieth let him glory in the Lord, but we have nothing to glory in, ſave the Croſſe of our Lord Jeſus, who hath ſaid, all mine are thine, and thine are mine, and I am glorified in them, and this is witneſſed through the Croſſe. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.17, 18. <hi>to the end. Iſaiah</hi> 9 13, 14. <hi>Iſa</hi> 45.25. <hi>John</hi> 17.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16, 17, 18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Pallard,</hi> I asked thee where ever <hi>Paul</hi> which thou ſaid gave forth orders to the Churches, &amp;c. had any Commiſſion to baptize, or where ever he ſaith in any place that he was ſent for that work? But on the contrary he ſaid, he was not ſent for that work, as it is left upon record under his hand-writing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17. For ſaith he there poſitively; Chriſt ſent me not to aptize, but to preach the Goſpel, and not with wiſdome of words neither, leſt the Croſſe of Chriſt ſhould be of none effect: And I asked thee what the Croſſe was, but thou could not tell, and why he was ſent to preach, and was neceſſirated to it, as he ſaith in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. For ſaith he, though I preach the Goſpel, I have nothing to glory of, but as he ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in the Croſſe where his Miniſtery ſtood, and ſaith he, There is a neceſſity laid upon me to preach the Goſpel, and wo is to me, if <hi>I</hi> preach it not, &amp;c 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16, 17, 18.</p>
            <p>But he did not ſay there was a neceſſity laid upon him to baptize, but he thankt God that he had baptized no more; by permiſſion he did that, and not by commiſſion, for he ſaid plainly, that Chriſt ſent him not to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, but to Preach, and he was ſent by the Spirit to Preach, and not by the Letter, as he did certifie to the brethren, and his certificate is to be ſeen for it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. but not to baptize.</p>
            <p>And he gave forth the Orders to the Church by the Spirit that ſent him to Preach; and where did he by that Spirit ever ſend forth any to baptize with water? but to Preach he did; and he was ſent by the Spirit and not by the Letter; and thou ſayes the Spirit and the Letter are inſeparable: but when the Son was revealed in him, he did not ſtand to conſult, neither did he ask leave of the Letter, but obeyed the Command of the Spirit, as it is left upon record, and the Letter did not give forth the Spirit, but the Spirit was before the Letter was: neither did the Letter ſend them to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118674:13"/>preach, but the Spirit did, and gave them power to ſpeak as the Oracles of God, but where did he ſay he was ſent to baptize, but onely to preach in the Croſſe, and that by the Spirit, and not by the Letter, for Chriſt was revealed within him, and ſent him to preach by his Spirit, and that which he preached he had not received of the Letter, but out of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of life, and from the flowings in of the Spirit; and he had known much of the Letter whilſt he perſecuted the Spirit, and when he received: he Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, he denyed himſelf and took up the Croſſe, and followed Chriſt in the Croſſe, and there continued in that Miniſtery by the Spirit, and were an able Miniſter of the New Covenant, not of the Letter but of the Spirit, and he ſaid, that the Goſpel which he preached unto them he had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it of man, neither was he taught it of man, but by the revelation of Jeſus Chriſt within him, and they did not croſſe him with the Letter, and ſay, how could they know that Chriſt was revealed in him, but received his Teſtiwony as from the Spirit, their Spirits witneſſing with his Spirit, and they were one in the ſeed, and their Goſpel was hid to them that were loſt; but the Letter is not hid, neither is it loſt; but the Goſpel is hid to thee <hi>Pallard,</hi> and to them that are loſt, who have the Letter but not the Spirit, for if any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt he is none of his, but many have the Letter but not the Spirit, as thou haſt the Letter but wants the Spirit, and all in thy nature, and are in the ſelf ſeparation from the Spirit which the Letter ſpeaks of, having not the Spirit, that ſaith the Bible is a Hiſtory, and the Letter and the Spirit are inſeparable, ſuch are in a form without the power, and ſo are as a body without the Spirit, and dead trees twice pluckt up by the roots, as it is written, but <hi>Paul</hi> was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Spirit and the Power, but preached in the power of the Spirit, that the bodies faith ſhould not ſtand in the wiſdome of mens words, but in the power of God, as it is written, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4, 5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.11, 12. <hi>and</hi> 15, 16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9 16, 17, 18. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>But where was he ſent by Commiſſion to baptize, and why was there a neceſſity laid upon him for the one, and not for the other, to baptize as well as to preach, ſeeing that the care of the Church was committed to him, and he knew the whole Councel of God? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16, 17, 18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Acts</hi> 20 28, 29.</p>
            <p>Then thou anſwered and ſaid, he baptized as well as he preached, for he baptized <hi>Criſpus</hi> and <hi>Gaius,</hi> and he baptized alſo the houſe of <hi>Stephanos;</hi> and thou began thereupon to make an oration to the people, and deviſe miſchief, and to tell lies, and ſaid to the people he denies the Scripture, and ſaid, <hi>Paul</hi> did not baptize, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thereupon the people ſome of them made anſwer, and ſaid, do not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe falſely: wherein did he deny the Scriptures, he did not ſay that <hi>Paul</hi> did not baptize, but asked where he was ſent to baptize, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Then taking thee with falſe accuſations and lyes in thy mouth, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof I ſpoke ſomething unto thee, and ſaid, how durſt thou lye ſo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, without any ground, but that it was ſuffered thee <hi>Pallard,</hi> to lay open thy folly that day to thy ſhame, and for the good of others that were lorded over by thee, till thy nakedneſſe and falſhood openly appeared, ſo that ſome of them did ſpeak to thee of it, and I then charged thee in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118674:13"/>of the Lord, either to make good what thou had ſaid, in falſely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing without any ground, or elſe for ever ſtop thy mouth, and be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of thy lies, and falſe accuſations in that thing, and alſo in others; and I ſaid, when did <hi>Paul</hi> receive any Commiſſion for to baptize, or when was he ſent for that work, becauſe himſelf ſaid he was not ſent to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, but to preach, and there was a neceſſity laid upon him for the one, and not for the other, and he had a Commiſſion to preach, and not to baptize, leſt by doing it by permiſſion without a command, and ſo abuſe his power, he gave God thanks that he had baptized no more, leſt they ſhould ſay he did it in his own Name, and without warrant or authority from God, becauſe he had no commiſſion from God for to do it; for he confeſſed and ſaid, that Chriſt ſent him not to baptize, but to preach, and for that he had a Command, and wo was unto him if he did neglect, and he was not to preach with the enticing words of mans wiſdome neither, but in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the Spirit and power, leſt the Croſſe ſhould be of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, in which his Miniſtery ſtood, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.14, 15, 16, 17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.18.</p>
            <p>And what he did by permiſſion was one thing, and what he did by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion was another, and ſometimes he did things by permiſſion, and not by Commiſſion, and what he did by permiſſion was as from the ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency, but what he did by Commiſſion was from the eternall power of eternity, and was the Lords, therefore he puts a difference between the man and the woman, and forbids the woman to ſpeak in the Church; he that can receive it let him: I told thee <hi>Pallard,</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> alſo circumciſed after he were a Miniſter of the Goſpel, as well as baptized, and he had as much ground for the one as the other, but no command for neither, and Chriſt was circumciſed outwardly, as well as baptized outwardly, and he miniſtred the circumciſion alſo, and were a Miniſter of the ſame, as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8.</p>
            <p>And I asked thee how thou followed Chriſt in that, to fulfill that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, and what account thou couldeſt give of it in the inward man as it is written, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11, 12. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Becauſe Chriſt miniſtred that, and they did witneſſe that Miniſtration through the Spirit in him, and ſo they were made compleat in the ſubſtance and life of all truth, through the Croſſe.</p>
            <p>And becauſe it is written, that death reigned from <hi>Adam</hi> untill <hi>Moſes,</hi> even over all that had not ſinned, after the ſimilitude of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, and the Law and the Prophets were till <hi>John, John</hi> ſucceeded them, and he came burning and ſhining, amongſt thoſe that were born of woman was not a greater than <hi>John,</hi> yet he that is leaſt in the kingdom of heaven is greater than he.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Pallard</hi> water baptizer, I asked thee how thou couldſt witneſſe to thoſe miniſtrations in the inward man, for the ſeed is but one, and how thou couldeſt witneſſe a paſſing from death unto life as they did that ſpoke forth the Scriptures, for they that had paſſed from death unto life, ſaid, that he that was born of God did not commit ſin, and they alſo ſaid, that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118674:14"/>he that committed ſin were of the devill, and thereby the two ſeeds was known, and the children of God was made manifeſt, and the children of the devill, by the operation of each ſeed ruling in them, and working forth through them, and they that had paſſed from death unto life, knew who was of God, and who was not, and ſo doth the ſame ſeed now, and they knew who did abide in darkneſſe and death, and ſo do they now who are in the Light life and power of the Truth, and they know that the Son of God is made manifeſt in them, and hath taken away their ſins, as they knew then that witneſſed the ſame through the Croſſe, who ſaid, that they dwelt in him; and he dwelt in them; but they did not know it by the dead Letter, but by the quickening Spirit, which is life, and was given them, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And they knew who were paſſed from death unto life, and that the Son of God was come, and had given them an underſtanding that they thereby might know him that was true, and they knew it not by the Letter, but by the Spirit, and they had the true knowledge of it in the eternall Truth, who affirmatively ſaid, we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt, this is the true God and eternall life, and not the Letter, but the Letter declareth of it, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.20.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Pallard</hi> I asked thee how it was with thee in deaths Dominion, becauſe it is written of deaths reigning from <hi>Adam</hi> untill <hi>Moſes</hi> over all who have not ſinned after the ſimilitude of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion, and what that death was, and reigned over in thee, how thou came from under it to know the Law which is perfect, and doth endure for ever, according to that in the conſcience, and is to be fulfilled in all that walk not after the fleſh but after the Spirit, and how thou came into the prophecies in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, becauſe it is written, the Law and the Prophets are till <hi>John,</hi> and the ſeed is but one, not ſeeds, but ſeed, and the promiſes are to the ſeed, fulfilled through death in the Miniſtery, by the Spirit in the croſſe, which cuts down and raiſeth up, and how thou came to know <hi>Johns</hi> Miniſtry ſet up with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in becauſe he came and doth come burning and ſhining, and there is a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe to rejoice in his Light for a ſeaſon, and how it was with thee in that Miniſtration; to know the ax laid to the root of the tree, and the tree to be cut down, and what that fallow ground in thee was which muſt be ript up, and I alſo asked thee what ſelf was, with the fruits and the ground of it, which the Croſſe is. Lo, I told thee the creation was a figure, and out of the ground ſprung up groſſe herbs, weeds, briers and thornes, &amp;c. And the ofspring was not the ground, the ofspring might be cut off, and there might ſpring up more fruits of the like nature again, ſo the fruits of ſelf might be cut off, and the ofspring was not the ground; and whileſt there was the ground and the roots in it unript up, more fruits would grow there of like nature alſo, therefore <hi>John</hi> ſaid, Rip up your fallow ground, make the rough places ſmooth, and prepare the way for the Lord to come into his Temple; that he may ſit as Refiner, I asked thee how thou paſt through that Miniſtery of <hi>John</hi> in the inward man, and what ſucced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118674:14"/>
               <hi>John,</hi> becauſe it is written, that the leaſt in the Kingdom of God is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than he, and ſome did witneſſe that they were ſet in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.6.</p>
            <p>And I ſaid unto thee, if thou was an Officer in the Church of the firſt born written in heaven, and were in the kingdom, thou couldeſt witneſſe to thoſe things, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22. and 28. <hi>Luk</hi> 17, 21.</p>
            <p>And liberty was granted to thee for to declare thy paſſages in the inward miniſtrations, if that thou couldeſt, that it might be for the good of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple there preſent, but thou could not ſpeak any thing at all concerning thoſe conditions, and inward miniſtrations, when thou was deſired, and ſeverall times urged to it, but all that thou could ſay, was to accuſe falſly, and ſaid, I denyed the Scriptures, and made that thy cover, which would not hide thee, but left thee bare, and thy nakedneſſe did then openly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; then I charged thee to be a lyar, and others witneſſed againſt thee for ſaying that I denyed the Scripture, when thou had no ground for it; but the devill was a lyer from the beginning, and abode not in the Truth, and thou lyer, who art out of the Truth, art of him, as thy deeds maketh thee manifeſt, <hi>John</hi> 8.44.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſtop thy mouth, and cover thy lips, and let ſhame ſtrike thee in the face, for ever, thou lyer, and falſe accuſer of the juſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul,</hi> who was a Miniſter of the new Covenant, not of the Letter, but of the the Spirit, he declared of his paſſages, and his grouth, and how he came out of one diſpenſation into another, and they that grew from one degree of grace and glory into another, they ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they knew no man after the fleſh, though they had known Chriſt after the fleſh, yet henceforth knew they him ſo no more, and they gave account of their paſſages and grouth, which thou could not do, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17, 18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16, 17.</p>
            <p>And the Apoſtle ſaid, give a reaſon of the hope that is in you to any man that ſhall ask you, and withall be ready to do it, that you may be able to comprehend with all Saints, what is the heighth and depth and breadth and length of the love of God.</p>
            <p>And thou <hi>Pallard,</hi> who art the great water baptizer, and all you out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward dippers, and outſide waſhers, who maketh clean the outſide of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy or veſſel, as the Scribes and the Phariſees did, and are hard bound up in a dead form; your ground is yet fallow, and to be ript up: And thou <hi>Pallard,</hi> and you dippers, ſprinklers with water, and outward baptizers, teachers and people, paſtors, deacons, and elders, and all and every one of you, from the higheſt to the loweſt, that cannot give account of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Miniſtrations and paſſages through the Croſſe, from death unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, and ſayes the Letter and the Spirit is inſeparable, you are yet out of the Saints conditions, and out of their life, and are in darkneſſe and deaths dominion, doing things by imitation in your wills, and are in that nature which acteth contrary to the light, and you ſet up formes contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Light, and according to your carnall apprehenſions, and are as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118674:15"/>a body without the Spirit, that ſay the Bible is a Hiſtory, and that ſayes the Letter and the Spirit are inſeparable, as <hi>Pallard</hi> the great water bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizer did.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord is that Spirit as is ſpoken of in the new Covenant, and glorious miniſtration, but the Lord is not the Letter, but he is the Spirit, and where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is Liberty, and we all with open face beholding as in a glaſſe the glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame image, from glory to glory, even by the Spirit of the Lord, and not by the Letter, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17, 18.</p>
            <p>You Dippers, ſprinklers, and water baptizers, that ſayes the Letter is the Spirit, or the Spirit and the Letter are inſeparable, as <hi>Pallard</hi> did, you are as a body without the Spirit that are in that nature which acteth contrary to the Light.</p>
            <p>Where is the gift of the holy Ghoſt amongſt you dippers, and outſide ſprinklers, and water baptizers? Where have any of you ſold your poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions yet, and laid down the price at your Apoſtles feet, as the water baptizers did, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>And where are you filled with the holy Ghoſt, that ſayes the Letter and the Spirit are inſeparable, and cals it a Hiſtory, as <hi>Pallard,</hi> did? Oh, what hypocrites are you, and how far ſhort are you of that miſtery? when were ever the place ſhaken where you were aſſembled together, when they had prayed the place was ſhaken where they were aſſembled together, and they were all filled with the holy Ghoſt, and ſpoke the word of God bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as the Spirit gave them utterance, and not the Letter, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.31. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.4. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.55.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, brethren, ſay they, look ye out ſeven men, full of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, whom we may appoint over you, but we will give our ſelves to the Miniſtery of the Word, and to prayer, but they did not bid them to chuſe out ſelf conceated proud men, full of fleſhly wiſedome, and vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, like unto you watermen that are in this generation, neither did they chooſe men full of the Letter, and brain-conceats as you do, but they chooſe men full of the holy Ghoſt, for the holy Ghoſt had all the Rule in the Church of God, and they chooſe <hi>Stephen</hi> a man full of Faith and the holy Ghoſt, and <hi>Philip,</hi> and <hi>Prochorus,</hi> and <hi>Nicanor,</hi> and <hi>Timon,</hi> and <hi>Parmenus,</hi> and <hi>Nicolas</hi> a Proſelite of <hi>Antioch,</hi> full of Faith and the holy Ghoſt was thoſe, and of good report, and they who were in the power of the Lord, and full of the wiſdome of God, and were endued with the holy Ghoſt, who had given themſelves up to ſerve God, in the miniſtery of the word, and not in the Miniſtry of the Letter, thoſe who were in the power of God, prayed, and laid their hands on thoſe that were ſent forth, and they were filled with the heavenly wiſdom, and with the holy Ghoſt, that none were able to reſiſt them, that ſtood in the power of the Spirit, and they were annointed by the Spirit, and the holy Ghoſt ſent them forth about the work of God in the Miniſtery of the Word; and the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118674:15"/>Word of God increaſed, which is not the Letter, as you baptizers ſay, but it is the Spirit which yet you are ignorant of, and as the Word of God increaſed, ſo the number of the Diſciples increaſed, and were mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed, and <hi>Stephen</hi> were full of Faith and power, that the wiſe men of the world, and great Diſputers of the Synagogue of the <hi>Libertines,</hi> and <hi>Cyrenians,</hi> and <hi>Alexandrians,</hi> and them of <hi>Silicia,</hi> and of <hi>Aſia</hi> diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with <hi>Stephen,</hi> and they were not able to reſiſt the wiſdom, and the Spirit by which he ſpake, and not the Letter, which wiſdom and Spirit, and laying on of hands, and ſending by the holy Ghoſt, and Miniſtry of the Word of eternall Life, Church and Church Officers that were made by the holy Ghoſt and is, which you Dippers, Sprinklers, and water baptizers are ignorant and know nothing of, though you have an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward form, you have not the power nor the Spirit, nor the Gifts as they had, but are as a Bell without a Clapper, or a body without the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that ſaith the Letter is the Word, and the Letter is the Spirit, and the Letter is a Hiſtory, and ſaith the Letter and the Spirit are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable, as <hi>Thomas Pallard</hi> great water Baptizer did, and it is evident you have not the gifts, nor the holy Ghoſt amongſt you, as the water baptizers ſpoken of in Scripture had, therefore are you but Phariſees, that have not the Spirit, and the holy Ghoſt as they had that ſpoke forth the Scriptures, and as they now have that liveth in the life of the Spirit; but you that ſay the Letter is the Word, and the Letter is the Spirit, and the Letter and the Spirit is inſeparable; You Baptizers with Water are out of the Divine Nature, and that faith ſpoken of, and out of the life and power of the holy Ghoſt, by which they did both preach, pray, and miniſter the Word, and lay on hands, and ſend forth, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3, 4. to the 9. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16, 17, 18. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.9. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.18. <hi>John</hi> 7.38. <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.25, 26. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.20, 27 <hi>Acts</hi> 6.3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10 <hi>Acts</hi> 4.31. <hi>Acts</hi> 8 17. <hi>Acts</hi> 19.6, 13 2, 3, 4. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32, 33, 34. <hi>Acts</hi> 20, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29. <hi>Hebrews</hi> 12.22, 23.28, 29.</p>
            <p>Read thoſe Scriptures, and let all who have a diſcerning given them in the eternall Truth, ſee whether the Dippers, Sprinklers, and water-Baptizers be not out of the life of them, and without the Falth ſpoken of, with the fruits and effects ſpoken of in them, and without the Power, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Spirit, Gifts, and holy Ghoſt ſpoken of in them, yea, or no; When did ever any of you Dippers, Sprinklers, or water Baptizers, give any the Gift of the holy Ghoſt by laying on of your hands or when did the holy Ghoſt ſend you to preach? that ſay the Letter is the Spirit; and the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the Spirit are inſeparable; here your ignorance doth appear in the Miniſtry of the Spirit: Read thoſe Scriptures before mentioned, and let them judge you, that ſay the Letter and the Spirit are inſeparable; and let them, and the Light of God in your conſciences which is pure judge you, and judge your empty formes without either life or power: Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine your ſelves, ye water Baptizers, whether ye be in the Faith or no, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:118674:16"/>
For it is written, that he that believeth, though he were dead, yet ſhall he live, and he that believeth, out of his belly ſhall flow the water of life, and this I witneſſe, and he that liveth and believeth ſhall never die, and he that believeth and is baptized ſhall be ſaved, but he that believeth not ſhall be damned; and he that is baptized, and believeth theſe ſigns ſhall follow them that believe, in my Name, ſaith Jeſus Chriſt, ſhall they caſt out divels, they ſhall ſpeak with new tongues: and the third ſign that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth after Baptiſm, the Baptiſm of Believers is this, They ſhal take up Serpents.</p>
            <p>And fourthy, They ſhall drink any deadly thing, it ſhall not hurt them.</p>
            <p>And the fifth ſign that followeth the Baptiſme of Believers is this, they ſhall lay hands on the ſick, and ſhall recover them; and theſe are not done by the Letter, but the Spirit, as it is witneſſed, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20. <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.25, 26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.20, 21.</p>
            <p>Now you water-Baptizers, examine your ſelves, whether you have faith or no; When were the divel caſt out in you, the Prince of the power of the Air, the Spirit that rules in thoſe that are dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, who are not yet quickened by the Spirit, for the Spirit doth quicken, but the Letter doth not, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.10, 11.</p>
            <p>When were the Serpents head bruiſed in you? And when were you cleanſed from the deadly poiſon, the poiſon of Aſpes that is under the tongue of thoſe that uſe deceit, which are of the ſeed of the Serpent, and in that nature and condition ſpoken of <hi>Romans</hi> 3.11, 13, 14, to the 19.</p>
            <p>When were you waſhed any one of you, and cleanſed with the water of the word, and by the Spirit of our God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6, 27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. that ſaith the Letter is the Word, and the Letter is the Spirit, and the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the Spirit are inſeparable? And when did you caſt out devils? When did you ſpeak with now tongues? When did you take up Serpents, and drink the deadly poiſon and it not hurt you, who yet are full that are one with the Serpent? and when did you ever recover the ſick by laying on of your hands upon them, who are not yet as the little Child that Chriſt took in his armes and bleſſed, learn your figure, and examine your faith; let the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in all your conſciences ſearch you, and it will let you ſee that you are full of luſt, but ſo was not the little Child, and the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in your Conſciences will let you ſee that you live in actuall tranſgreſſions, ſo did not the little Childe, and the Light will let you ſee your inward diſeaſe; and that you are not healed and cured, and made whole, and bleſſed as the little Childe then was; and except ye become as that little Child, ye ſhall in no wiſe enter into the kingdome of God; for there ſhall in no wiſe enter into it any thing that defileth, neither whatſoever worketh abomination, or maketh a lye, but they which are written in the Lambs Book of life; he that can receive it, let him, <hi>Revelation</hi> 2.26, 27, 28, 29. <hi>Revelation</hi> 21.27.</p>
            <p>And how far ſhort in practice of thoſe water Baptizers ſpoken of in the fourth of the <hi>Acts</hi> are you Dippers, Sprinklers, and water Babtizers,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118674:16"/>in this generation? For as many of the Water Baptizers there ſpoken of then, as were poſſeſſors of Lands or Houſes ſold them, and brought the prices of things that were ſold, and laid down at their Apoſtles feet, and diſtribution was made to every man according as he had need, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32, 33, 34, 35, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If you imitate them in one thing, why do you not follow them in all? But where have any of you Dippers, Sprinklers, and water Baptizers, Imitaters followed them in their practice in that? You can take what you will and leave what you will, as your conceats and fancies are; Oh, hypocrites, which make clean the outſide of the cup and platter, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy or veſſel, but inwardly you are full of extortion, luſt, envy, pride, and acceſſe, the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in your conſciences will accuſe you of it, and let you ſee it, rooted and ſeated within you in the earthly dark parts and that Light is your Teacher, loving it, and obeying it, but that Light is your condemnation, hating it, and diſobeying it, who act contrary to it, and love the deeds of darkneſſe rather than the Light, with the Light you are all ſeen and comprehended; your covers will not hide you now, you water baptizers; if you ſew all the Fig-leaves together that you have, or outward imitations, and taken on Commands from the Letter by your wills, they will not hide you who are in that nature, which acteth contrary to the Light, with the Light are you ſeen to be out of the life of what you do profeſſe, as the Phariſees was: You are bare, that wants the cloathing of the Spirit, and ſayes the Letter and the Spirit are inſeparable.</p>
            <p>Wo to you all Formaliſts, that are out of the Light, and covered with the Letter and earth, and not with the Spirit of the Lord, <hi>Read Iſa.</hi> 30.1. <hi>Math.</hi> 23.25.</p>
            <p>You water Baptizers are ſeated in your conceits, and ſtabliſhed in your ſelf-righteouſneſſe, as the Phariſees was, and appears righteous outwardly unto men, as they did, but within ye are full of deceit, pride, luſt, hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie and iniquity as they was, with the Light you are ſeen and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.27.</p>
            <p>And the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in all your conſciences will let you ſee where you are, and reprove you in ſecret, for acting contrary to it, and the Light of God in thy conſcience, <hi>Thomas Pallard,</hi> great water Baptizer, and all that are in thy Nature, form and hypocriſie, the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in all your conſciences, which checks and reproves you in ſecret for ſin and evill, will let you ſee the hypocriſie and iniquity that yet is unwaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of your hearts.</p>
            <p>You have waſhed the outſide in the Water, but yet are in the evill na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in all your conſciences will let you ſee the ſame; which Light, if you love it, and obey it, and ſubmit to the Teachings of it, will bring you to the knowledge of the eternall Truth, and out of your conceated formes, to take up the Croſſe to, your wills; and earthly wiſedomes, to die to the world and all your pride and vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, that Light which lets you ſee the deeds of darkneſſe, and the evill of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118674:17"/>your hearts, that Light is your Teacher, which ſtands out of all evill, that Light is your Teacher, your that love it and bring your deeds to it to be tryed, that your works may be wrought in God, that light is your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, all you that hate it, and act contrary to it, who love the deeds of darkneſſe rather than the Light, <hi>John</hi> 1.9. <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.12. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19, 20.</p>
            <p>Now you have time, prize it, and take heed of ſinning againſt the Light, and <hi>Pallard,</hi> and all in that nature, give over deceiving the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and keeping them in a dead form, without either life or power, leſt their ſouls periſh and be loſt, thou that ſayes the Letter and the Spirit are inſeparable and a Hiſtory art ignorant of the ſoul and the miſtery, give over I warn thee, and charge thee, in the preſence of the Lord, and all in thy nature, as you will anſwer it before the judgment ſeat of Chriſt, I ſhall there be a witneſſe againſt you if you will not take warning; now you have time, prize it: For hereby know we that we dwell in him, and he in us, by his Spirit which he hath given us, and not by the Letter but by the eternall Spirit, hereby is our love made perfect, that we may have boldneſſe in the day of judgement, as they ſaid, who were in Chriſt before us; who ſaid, as he is, ſo are we in this preſent world, witneſſed in the eternall power by the Spirit, perfect in love, and compleat in him who is the head of all Principally and power, as it is written, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.24. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.16, 17. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.9, 10.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Pallard,</hi> where thou ſaid <hi>Paul</hi> had attained to ſuch high Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and diſcoveries, and were taken up into the third heaven, as is there ſpoken of, yet afterwards, though ſaid, he cryed out of his infirmities and ſaid, he had nothing to glory in but his infirmities, and had a prick in the fleſh, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I anſwered thee again, by way of Querie to that, and asked thee if it was <hi>Paul</hi> that was taken into the third heaven, or ſome other that he there ſpoke of, and gloried in at that time, and in that thy mouth was ſtopt, for I of thee received not anſwer to it again, there was the deceit in thee ſilenc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at that time, as well as before, and thou had nothing for to glory in but thy ſhame and folly, as it did openly appear in ſo much, that a member of the body cryed out againſt thee, or the head, to ſee thy folly, as the Aſſe cryed out againſt <hi>Balaam,</hi> and ſpoke to ſhew him his folly, and the poor creature ſaid, Had not he been his Aſſe, and carried him ſo long? when did he ever know him do ſo before? And when the Lord opened <hi>Balaams</hi> eyes, he ſaw his folly, and if the Lord open thine eyes, thou may plainly ſee thine, who thy ſelf haſt ridden and lorded over poor creatures ſo long, and had them at thy command, yet at that very time one was made to ſpeak to thee, that had been ridden on or lorded over by thee, and did reprove thee, to ſee thee ſo ſhew forth thy folly: When was it ever known that he did ſo before to thee at ſuch a time? But it is but that the Scriptures may be fulfilled; as it is written, they ſhall proceed no further that reſiſt the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118674:17"/>Truth for their folly ſhall thereby he made manifeſt to men, as thine was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Truth at that time, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8, 9 And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtond up for the Truth to reſiſt thy deceit, though thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> appeared, thou art ready to put them out of thy ſervice, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it, if it be ſo, they may rejoice to ſee thy madneſſe and folly made manifeſt; thou was at that time without the Sword as <hi>Balaam</hi> was, and the poor creatures who had been hard bound down under thee, at that time rejoicee, and it they continue their joy will increaſe, and bleſſed are all they that ſuffer for righteouſneſſe ſake, and ſaith the Lord, all thoſe that are caſt out for my Names ſake, I will appear to their joy, and to the ſhame of all their falſe pretended Brethren, that ſaith, let the Lord be glorified by them, in ſcorn, contempt, or diſdain, in nature like unto the Jews, <hi>Iſa</hi> 66.5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.10, 11, 12. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.22, 23.</p>
            <p>But as touching the place of Scripture where thou ſaid <hi>Paul</hi> was in ſuch Raptures, and high diſcoveries caught up into the third heaven, and taken up into Paradiſe, and after cryed out of his infirmities, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>As I ſaid then, ſo ſay I ſtill, let all the wiſe hearted read it, and judge, whether <hi>Paul</hi> ſpoke that of himſelf, or ſome other, for to it thou would not return me an anſwer, when I demanded it of thee: But <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf plainly there ſaith, that he knew a man in Chriſt above fourteen years ago, whether in the body or out of the body, he could not tell, but had <hi>Paul</hi> there ſpoken of himſelf, he could have told if it had been him, and he did not ſay that he was caught into the third heavens, and taken up into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and afterwards fell out of it again, to cry out of a thorn in his ſide, or a prick in the fleſh, and ſay he had nothing to glory in but his infirmities as thou <hi>Pallard</hi> and darkneſſe conceives, Read and ſee, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> there ſpeaks of another, as it is plain: for ſaith he, firſt I knew a man, ſuch a one as he is there ſpeaking of: he ſpeaks of the time alſo: and it was above 14. years ago, or bypaſt from that time, that he was there ſpeaking of him, and he ſaith, that though he ſpoke of him and his being in Chriſt, ſo long ſince from that time, yet he knew not whether he were in the body or no; but in that place he ſaid, that God knew whether he was in the body or out of it; but he there ſaith, that ſuch a one was caught into the third heaven, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.2.</p>
            <p>And further he there ſaith, he knew ſuch a man, whether in the body, or out of the body he could not tell, God knew, as he ſaith in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. But had <hi>Paul</hi> ſpoken of himſelf he could have told how it had been with him: yet in the ſixth place he ſaith, that ſuch a one was caught up into Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe; and in the ſeventh place it doth appear, that he was a dear friend to <hi>Paul,</hi> and told him what he heard in the third heaven, and in the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, but it is not expreſſed there, for he ſayes they was ſuch words as was not lawfull to utter, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4.</p>
            <p>Then in the eighth place he ſaith, that of ſuch a one he would glory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.5.</p>
            <p>But ſaith he, of my felf I have nothing to glory in, but mine infirmities,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118674:18"/>yet he had wherewithall to glory, but he forbore at that time, leſt any man ſhould think of him above what he ſaw him to be, as he there ſaith, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12 6.</p>
            <p>And he that were taken up into the third heaven, and into the Paradiſe, and heard ſuch words that was not lawfull to utter, were an intimate friend of <hi>Pauls</hi> that did make it known unto him, and in him he gloried, who were in ſuch a perfect ſtate as that, though he had nothing in himſelf to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of; but his infirmities that he took pleaſure in; thoſe infirmities was not ſins, as darkneſſe taketh them to be, but his infirmities which he glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in, and took pleaſure in, was in neceſſities, in diſtreſſes, in perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, and in reproaches for Chriſts ſake, as it is ſet down plainly in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10. read and ſee: and to be reproached and perſecuted for righteouſneſſe ſake, was a bleſſed thing as Chriſt himſelf ſaid, and as you may read and ſee, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.10.11, 12.</p>
            <p>And bleſſed are thoſe that are in ſuch infirmities, for ſuch a cauſe as it is written, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6 22, 23. And if ye be reproached for the Name of Chriſt; happy are you, for the Spirit of glory and of God reſteth upon you, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.13, 14. and <hi>Paul</hi> being in that happineſſe gloried therein, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; and he did moſt gladly glory in thoſe infirmities that the power of Chriſt might reſt upon him, and therefore in them he took pleaſure, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9, 10.</p>
            <p>And thou <hi>Pallard,</hi> Water Baptizer, and the reſt, denyed Perfection in this life in the new creation, and working of God, for we know that we are the workmanſhip of God, created in Chriſt Jeſus, and he that is in Chriſt Jeſus is a new creature, old things are paſſed away, and all things are become new, as it is written, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10. to the end. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16, 17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21 1, to the 6. verſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pallard</hi> thou and all that denyeth perfection, you deny that which Chriſt came to accompliſh by his death, reſurrection and aſcenſion, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery in the Spirits of his Saints, and in the new Covenant, for if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection could have been by the Leviticall Prieſthood, for under it the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple received the Law, what further need was there that another Prieſt ſhould riſe after the order of <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> and not be called after the Order of Aaron, for the Prieſthood being changed, there is made of neceſſity a change of the Law alſo: for he of whom theſe things are ſpoken pertaineth to another Tribe, of which no man gave attendance at the Altar; for it is evident that our Lord ſprang out of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> of which Tribe <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpoke nothing concerning Prieſthood, and it is yet far more evident, for that after the ſimilitude of <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> there ariſeth another Prieſt, who is made not after the Law of a carnall commandement, but after the power of an endleſſe life, for he teſtifieth thou art a Prieſt for ever after the order of <hi>Melchiſedeck;</hi> for there is verily a diſannulling of the Law or comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement going before, which ſtood outward in types, tithes, ſhadowes and figures, for the weakneſſe and unprofitableneſſe thereof, for the Law out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly made nothing perfect, but the bringing in of a better hope did,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118674:18"/>make perfect; which is in the miſtery Chriſt, the hope of glory, and the new Covenant, and he that hath this hope in him purifieth himſelf even as he is pure, and he that ſanctifieth, and they that are ſanctified are of him, and he is not aſhamed to call them brethren, and he hath for ever perfected them that are ſanctified; Read thoſe Scriptures, and let them judge thy ignorance <hi>Pallard,</hi> and the ignorance of all you that deny perfection to be attained to by Chriſt in the new Covenant, and Goſpel miniſtration, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.11, 12, 13. to the 20. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27, 28. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.10, 11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.10, 11, 12, 13, 14. &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6, 7. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God willing more abundantly to ſhew to the heirs of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe the immutability of his Councel, when he made Promiſe of it to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> confirmed it with an oath, and ſaid unto him, Walk before me and be thou perfect, and ſee who the heirs of the Promiſe are, which hath right to it, <hi>Gal</hi> 3.29 <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.28. which thing in the Covenant is ſo confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the ſeed, that by two immutable things in which it was impoſſible for God to lye, we might have a ſtrong-conſolation who are children of the Promiſe, as <hi>Iſack</hi> was: who are of the ſeed and heirs according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, who have fled for the Refuge to lay hold upon that ſet before us, which is moſt ſure and ſtedfaſt, and maketh an entrance to that within the Vail, where the forerunner for us is entered, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.13. to the end, and we are in him and he in us, and we are made perfect in one, and are in union and Fellowſhip with the Father and the Son, as they witneſſed, <hi>John</hi> 17.10. 2 <hi>John</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>And ſaith Jeſus our Lord, At that day ye ſhall know that I am in my Father, and you in me, and I in you, <hi>John</hi> 14.20.</p>
            <p>And there is there that bear record, the Father, the Word and the holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one in the Kingdom amongſt the Saints, even the Kingdom of heaven within, as it is written, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.6, 7; 8, 9, 10, 11 <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.21.</p>
            <p>And ſaith Chriſt to the Father, the glory which thou gaveſt me, I have given them, that they may be one even as we are one, I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one, <hi>John</hi> 17.23, 24,</p>
            <p>Chriſt Jeſus in his Sermon upon the Mount, he taught the People, and ſaid unto them, be ye perfect, as your heavenly Father is perfect, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48.</p>
            <p>And they did not croſſe him in his Doctrine, and ſay they could not be perfect, as people ſay now in this generation.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Abraham</hi> was ninety and nine years old, the Lord appeared unto <hi>Abraham</hi> and ſaid, I am the Almighty God, walk before me, and be thou perfect, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Abraham</hi> did not croſſe the Word of God, and ſay he could not be perfect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> he ſaw that perfection was to be attained, and he preſſed after it,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118674:19"/>and did not tell people it was not poſſible it ſhould be attained unto, as the dark Teachers of the world do now, that labours to keep people in darkneſs and unbelief. But <hi>Paul</hi> in his grouth, as ſome were in Chriſt and grown up to perfection before him, but he preſſed after it, and ſaid, as many as are perfect be thus minded, to preſſe on others to come up to perfection, for Chriſt Jeſus when he aſcended up on high, he led captivity captive, and gave gifts unto men, for that very end to edifie the Body, till they come into the fulneſſe of the meaſure of the ſtature of Chriſt, and unto a perfect man in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.14, 15. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> was a perfect man, as God himſelf ſaid; and <hi>Noah</hi> was a perfect man in his generation; and <hi>David</hi> ſaid, Mark the perfect man, then there was perfect men, and the end of ſuch are peace, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.13. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 20.3. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9. <hi>Job</hi> 1.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.37.</p>
            <p>But the tranſgreſſors ſhall be deſtroyed together; the end of the wicked ſhall be cut off, and turned into hell, and be burned with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone: Read <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.38. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.</p>
            <p>Read thoſe Scriptures and ſee your portion that plead for ſin, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in unrighteouſneſſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.15. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.8, 9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.28. to the end: <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5, 8, 9. <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.</p>
            <p>See your portion you that deſire to continue in wickededneſſe, and take your reward, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. to the end. Read and underſtand all that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to love God, and take warning whilſt you have time, now you have time, prize it, and plead not for ſin which is the devils kingdom.</p>
            <p>And thou <hi>Pallard;</hi> thou and all that denieth perfection are ignorant of the Life of Truth, and the Miniſtry of the Saints, and croſſeth the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of God, and of Chriſt, and croſſeth the Covenant of grace, and the Miniſtry of the Saints, for they preached wiſdom amongſt them that was perfect, as it is written, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2 6, 7.</p>
            <p>And Chriſt in his Sermon upon the Mount bade them be perfect, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48. And the Apoſtle ſaid, Finally my Brethren, farewell, be perfect, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11.</p>
            <p>And they ſaid, Let us go on to perfection, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. And they did go on to it, for they came to the innumerable company of Angels, to the Church of the firſt born written in heaven, to God the Judge of all, and to the Spirits of juſt men made perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22.23. And they ſaid, therein was their love made perfect, that they might have boldneſſe in the day of judgement, for as he was ſo was they in that preſent world: 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.16, 17. And they were without fault before the throne of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and no gull was found in their mouths, that were redeemed from amongſt men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. being the firſt fruits unto God and to the Lamb, <hi>verſe</hi> 4, 5.</p>
            <p>And they ſaid to others that were in their grouth, as he that hath called you is holy, ſo be ye holy in all manner of converſation, and this is witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, See <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.3, 4, 5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13, 14, 15, 16.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:118674:19"/>
And thou <hi>Pallard,</hi> and all that ſaith the Bible is a Hiſtory, and ſaith the Letter and the Spirit are inſeparable, and all that preaches the Letter and not the Spirit, and denyeth perfection by Chriſt in the new Covenant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11, 18. All ſuch as you are, do bring a contrary doctrine to Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and all you that are againſt perfection, you are againſt the new Covenant, and you deny the Scriptures therein, that deny per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and you deny the Doctrine of Chriſt, and the Apoſtles, and the end of Chriſts death, reſurrection, aſcenſion, and the Church of the firſt born written in heaven, as is proved by the Scriptures, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 23, 24, 28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.16, 17, 18, 19, 29, 21, 22.</p>
            <p>And we deny you, and all that deny fellowſhip with the Father and the Son, and we are not to receive ſuch into our houſes, nor to bid them God ſpeed, but to hold them and you all ſuch accurſed, as it is written and as you may read, 2 <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.10, 11. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſilence all fleſh, and deceit, and ſtop your mouths, ſay not but that you are warned, leſt I be a witneſſe againſt you before the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat of Chriſt, in the terrible day of the Lords feirce wrath and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation; and as I told thee <hi>Pallard</hi> at thy going forth of the door, that ſhal ſtand for thee. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.14. to the end. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.15.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.17. 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 6.23. <hi>Iude</hi> 14, 15.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. F.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written in</hi> Warwick <hi>ſhire</hi> 
                  <date> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the eigth month, Octob. 4. 1654.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:118674:20"/>
            <head>The ſealed are the LORDS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THerefore, thus ſaith the Lord, Behold I have laid in <hi>Sion,</hi> and do lay there a chief corner ſtone, Elect and precious, he that believeth on him ſhall not be confounded, and the Foundation of God ſtandeth ever, and hath this Seal ſet upon it, the Lord knoweth who are his, and they that are Sealed, they know him by his indwellings in them, and we know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us the gift and the Seal, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding by which we know that we are in him, and he in us, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt, and this is true God and life eternall, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and witneſſed, See 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4; 5, 6, 7. to the 11. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.2, 3. <hi>John</hi> 6.27. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.24. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.20.</p>
            <p>God hath alſo out of his free love given to every man a talent, or a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of grace to improve, and Chriſt is the true light that enlighteneth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man that cometh into the world, and he that obeyeth the Light is led out of darkneſſe into the eternall life, and entereth into Covenant with God, and is Sealed, and enters into the joy of his Lord, as it is written and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed: <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.14, 15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Titus</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.5, 9. <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5, 8, 9 <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.19, 20, 21. to the end. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>But he that hateth the Light he is the unprofitable Servant that accounts God a hard Maſter, but though he do ſo, he hath the Light manifeſted in his conſcience, which lets him ſee the deeds of darkneſſe, and not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, that will be his condemnation: <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0.</p>
            <p>It doth not teach him, becauſe he doth not love it nor obey it; therefore becauſe he hath it and doth not obey it, when God takes away his own, he will be found juſt in the condemnation of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oothfull, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the wicked; for it will ſtand with his Juſtice ſo to do, let God be juſt, and every man that hates the Light be found a lyar, he that hateth the Light hath it, as the unprofitable ſervant had the Talent given him, to improve, and did not improve it, and ſo it was taken from him that had not, and given to him that had; the Talent was taken from the unprofitable ſervant that had not improved it, and was given to him that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118674:20"/>had improved his Talents, and he entered into the joy of his Lord, but the unprofitable ſervant was caſt, and is to be caſt into utter darkneſſe, where ſhall be weeping and wailing and gnaſhing of teeth, as it is written <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>But he was not caſt into utter darkneſſe becauſe he had not the Gift gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, but becauſe he had it and did not make uſe of it to ſerve him with it that gave it unto him; and the manifeſtation of the Spirit is given to every man to proſit withall, if he uſe it aright in the ſervice, but all doth not profit, becauſe all doth not obey it, and Chriſt is the true Light that enligteneth every one that cometh into the world, and lets him ſee his ſins, and the deeds of darkneſſe: but every man doth not love the Light, ſo as in all things to obey it, and there is his condemnation: not becauſe he hath not the Light made manifeſt to the view of his underſtanding, but becauſe it is made manifeſt to the view of his underſtanding, and he loves darkneſſe rather than Light, he that obeyeth the Light is led out of darkneſſe, and hath ſalvation: <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.8.9.</p>
            <p>But he that diſobeyeth the Light, and receives not the Truth in the love of it, but ſerves unrighteouſneſſe, he and all ſuch are for damnation, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19, 20. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.9. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.12:</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
